<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>2024s on Hexops' devlog</title><link>https://devlog.hexops.com/2024/</link><description>Recent content in 2024s on Hexops' devlog</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://devlog.hexops.com/2024/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Mach v0.3 released - Zig game engine &amp; graphics toolkit</title><link>https://devlog.hexops.com/2024/mach-v0.3-released/</link><pubDate>Fri, 02 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://devlog.hexops.com/2024/mach-v0.3-released/</guid><description>&lt;p>Mach is a Zig game engine &amp;amp; graphics toolkit for building high-performance &amp;amp; modular games, visualizations, and desktop/mobile apps. &lt;a href="https://machengine.org/">Learn more&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We are working towards Mach 1, and have just released v0.3 which includes &lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/mach/milestone/5?closed=1">6 months of work&lt;/a> - here are the highlights!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="coming-soon-intro-to-2d-gamedev-workshop">Coming soon: intro to 2D gamedev workshop&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The first-ever &lt;strong>intro to 2D gamedev workshop using Mach&lt;/strong> will be hosted at the &lt;a href="https://sycl.it/">Software You Can Love&lt;/a> conference in Milan, Italy, May 14-17. The workshop will use Mach&amp;rsquo;s currently in-development higher level 2D graphics APIs.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="imglink" href="https://sycl.it/">&lt;img src="https://devlog.hexops.com/img/2024/sycl-workshop.png">&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in Zig or Mach, then &lt;a href="https://sycl.it/agenda/workshops/intro-to-2d-gamedev/">check out the SYCL conference&lt;/a>! It&amp;rsquo;s an amazing experience, a great opportunity to meet a ton of Zig community members, core team members, as well as enjoy some of the best food that Italy has to offer!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="community-highlight-pixi-and-scoopems">Community highlight: Pixi and Scoop&amp;rsquo;ems&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/foxnne">@foxxne&lt;/a> is an early adopter of &lt;a href="https://machengine.org/core/">Mach core&lt;/a>, largely pushing it to its limits. They make use of Mach&amp;rsquo;s new experimental sysgpu graphics API (which we intend to be a successor/descendant of WebGPU), as well as other libraries like flecs and dear-imgui. They&amp;rsquo;re developing &lt;a href="https://github.com/foxnne/pixi">Pixi&lt;/a> - a pixel art editor:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a class="imglink" href="https://devlog.hexops.com/img/2024/pixi1.png">&lt;img src="https://devlog.hexops.com/img/2024/pixi1.png">&lt;/a>
&lt;a class="imglink" href="https://devlog.hexops.com/img/2024/pixi2.png">&lt;img src="https://devlog.hexops.com/img/2024/pixi2.png">&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>And have used it to make games like &lt;a href="https://github.com/foxnne/scoop-ems">Scoop&amp;rsquo;ems&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;video loop controls height="4000px">
&lt;source src="https://media.machengine.org/showcase/scoopems.mp4" type="video/mp4">
&lt;/video>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/sponsors/foxnne">@foxxne&lt;/a> is making awesome tools and games in Zig, pushing things to their limits, I encourage watching &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7K9Vzcr7vJg">how humble Colton is when speaking about their work&lt;/a>. We are very excited to make Mach support foxxne&amp;rsquo;s projects better in the future, and enable others to build things like this too.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Please consider &lt;a href="https://github.com/sponsors/foxnne">sponsoring their work on GitHub&lt;/a> - you could be their second-ever sponsor!&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="mach-core">Mach core&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://machengine.org/core/">Mach core&lt;/a> aims to provide just a window, input, and truly cross-platform graphics API.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We think of it as an alternative/competitor to the classic options of SDL+OpenGL, GLFW+Vulkan, etc. Today, it&amp;rsquo;s not quite there yet - it uses GLFW behind the scenes for desktop support, and WebGPU as its graphics API, but we&amp;rsquo;re actively working on making it a genuine competitor written in Zig.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this release, it saw general bug fixes - as well as some &lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/libmach">libmach&lt;/a> development - which aims to provide a C API to both Mach core and engine APIs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sysgpu">sysgpu&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In Mach v0.2, we announced an experiment - that we were working on a WebGPU implementation written in Zig, as an alternative to using Dawn (Google Chrome&amp;rsquo;s WebGPU implementation.) In the past 6 months, this experiment saw an immense amount of development and exceeded our expectations!&lt;/p>
&lt;a class="imglink" href="https://machengine.org/pkg/mach-sysgpu">
&lt;picture>&lt;source media="(prefers-color-scheme: dark)" srcset="https://machengine.org/assets/mach/sysgpu-dark.svg">&lt;img alt="mach-sysgpu" src="https://machengine.org/assets/mach/sysgpu-light.svg" style="height:7rem;margin-top:1rem">&lt;/picture>
&lt;/a>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://machengine.org/pkg/mach-sysgpu/">sysgpu&lt;/a> today is a nearly fully-functional WebGPU native implementation (minus browser-level safety checks), thanks to &lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/mach-sysgpu/graphs/contributors">two amazing contributors&lt;/a>. It has functional D3D12, Vulkan, Metal, and OpenGL backends. It has it&amp;rsquo;s own WGSL shader compiler, and nearly all mach-core examples are runnable using it. We&amp;rsquo;ve even seen real applications (the Pixi pixel editor from foxxne, for example) begin to adopt it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As we continued development of it over the past six months, we identified key design tradeoffs where we could differ from WebGPU&amp;rsquo;s API choices and gain a faster, more modern, featureful graphics API. As a result, we&amp;rsquo;ve come to view sysgpu as a leaner and meaner &lt;em>successor and descendant of&lt;/em> WebGPU for native graphics, rather than just another implementation of it. As a result, it builds on the back of WebGPU&amp;rsquo;s design choices, but ultimately has its own distinct API and will not be ABI-compatible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We have plans to alleviate some &lt;em>major&lt;/em> pain points of WebGPU, specifically around pipeline creation / descriptor boilerplate, supporting push constants when available via a better API design (not as an extension), a more integrated/seamless approach to binding resources to shaders with type-correctness, and more.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We are also evaluating using Zig itself as the shading language, instead of WGSL, and are looking to enable fully offline shader compilation as an optional feature.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>sysgpu is still under heavy development, particularly all of the &amp;lsquo;successor/descendant&amp;rsquo; API design choices noted above have not been implemented yet. It is disabled in the v0.3 release by default, and after this release we plan to invest more aggressively in it - so expect more details and specifics to come soon.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="sysaudio">sysaudio&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>As a bit of background, &lt;a href="https://machengine.org/pkg/mach-sysaudio/">mach-sysaudio&lt;/a> started out as Zig bindings to Andrew Kelley&amp;rsquo;s fantastic C library &lt;a href="https://github.com/andrewrk/libsoundio">libsoundio&lt;/a>, but ultimately it grew to stand on its own two feet - becoming a brand new library written in Zig from first-principles and the ground-up to achieve similar goals: providing just low-level audio input/output, nothing else. It saw a good deal of polish in this iteration:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/mach-sysaudio/pull/33">SIMD sample conversion support&lt;/a> - and sample conversion is now explicitly optional (so the default is to work with the driver&amp;rsquo;s active audio format.)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Major API design improvements&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed issues with microphone/input devices, specifically multi-channel devices on macOS with CoreAudio.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Fixed &lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/mach/issues?q=is%3Aissue+sysaudio+is%3Aclosed+milestone%3A%22Mach+0.3%22">various issues&lt;/a> with the WASAPI/Windows backend.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h3 id="audio-synthesizer-hack-project">Audio synthesizer hack-project&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>As a quick hack project over the holidays, I leveraged Mach&amp;rsquo;s audio libraries, reading midi input from a piano keyboard, synthesizing audio using Zig code / Mach, and playing it back through digital piano speakers. Here&amp;rsquo;s a few vertical videos of me being silly &amp;amp; having fun with it (skip to 2:24 to hear how I think a Ziguana might sound!):&lt;/p>
&lt;iframe width="720" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/b8WDjaZC1C8?si=SgojGMwdD_lfncgn" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h2 id="nominated-zig-versions">Nominated Zig versions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Mach has always needed a sweet-spot between stable Zig and nightly Zig, a better balance of latest-and-greatest features and bug fixes, but less of a moving target than nightly Zig. To address this, we formalized how we &lt;a href="https://devlog.hexops.com/2024/announcing-nominated-zig/">nominate Zig versions&lt;/a> for use, enabling others to synchronize their Zig version with the one Mach supports more easily.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="mach-engine-as-a-standard-library-of-modules">Mach engine as a standard library of modules&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We began &lt;a href="https://machengine.org/engine/stdlib/">documenting&lt;/a> how we view Mach &lt;em>engine&lt;/em> as a standard library of modules for game development, and how we&amp;rsquo;ll enable you to use just the parts you wish. This is a small-but-important step in showcasing how the engine&amp;rsquo;s higher level APIs will be more modular than the monolithic big engines of today.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="entity-component-system">Entity component system&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The Mach entity component system provides a key role in Mach&amp;rsquo;s modularity, in this iteration it saw numerous polish / bug fix improvements - the ability to actually query entities, a more clear/concise API, etc. It is still under heavy development, however.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="machmath">mach.math&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/mach/tree/main/src/math">mach.math&lt;/a> was introduced to the Mach standard library: a custom math library tailored towards our graphics API conventions, matrix representations, coordinate systems, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Today it includes many of the basics: vectors, matrices, quaternions - though it is still missing some basic tablestakes. It also has ray-triangle intersection, and we intend to expand it to cover more general collision utilities later.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A new set of &lt;a href="https://machengine.org/engine/math/">math docs&lt;/a> were added to the website with some cute diagrams/visualizations.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="machgfxsprite">mach.gfx.Sprite&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/mach/blob/main/src/gfx/Sprite.zig">mach.gfx.Sprite&lt;/a> was introduced, which is the start of a 2D sprite-rendering module. It is largely usable, though we anticipate its API to change a fair amount and are looking to add animated sprite support among other key features.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It has been useful in letting us test basic rendering of hundreds of thousands of sprites, each as separate entities with their own transformation matrices calculated CPU-side, and get more of an end-to-end feel for how things are looking with our ECS:&lt;/p>
&lt;iframe width="720" height="480" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/ciuSYf7dcuE?si=SgojGMwdD_lfncgn" title="YouTube video player" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen>&lt;/iframe>
&lt;h2 id="machgfxtext">mach.gfx.Text&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Development of a basic text rendering module is underway, but not ready for use yet.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="status-of-simple-2d-game-support">Status of &amp;lsquo;simple 2D game&amp;rsquo; support&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In short, we&amp;rsquo;re still working on it. More to come soon.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="general-project-maintenance">General project maintenance&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Two new examples &lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/mach-core/tree/main/examples/rgb-quad">rgb-quad&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/mach-core/tree/main/examples/textured-quad">textured-quad&lt;/a> showing off super basic 2D rendering were added.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Began to formulate our &lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/mach/issues/989">hardware support plans&lt;/a>, such as when we will target certain SIMD instruction sets.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>All of our &lt;code>build.zig&lt;/code> scripts went through a great deal of changes and improvements, as Zig&amp;rsquo;s build system and package manager matured greatly.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Various &lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/mach/milestone/5?closed=1">other issues&lt;/a> were addressed.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="a-personal-note">A personal note&lt;/h2>
&lt;div style="display: flex;">
&lt;a href="https://github.com/slimsag">
&lt;img style="width: 420px" src="https://machengine.org/img/slimsag-profile.png">
&lt;/a>
&lt;div>
&lt;p>I work a normal tech job, and most days after I sign off from work I go online to build Mach, often like working two jobs. I've been doing this for a few years now, and dreaming of being able to build Mach for a decade before that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>FOSS &lt;a href="https://devlog.hexops.com/2021/increasing-my-contribution-to-zig-to-200-a-month#i-grew-up-playing-linux-games-like-mania-drive">is in my roots&lt;/a> and I believe we should own our tools, they should empower &lt;em>us&lt;/em>-not be part of &lt;a href="https://kristoff.it/blog/the-open-source-game/">the 'open source' game&lt;/a> which is all too prevelant today (even among 'open source' engines.) Mach &lt;em>needs&lt;/em> to be for people like you and me-it needs to genuinely be &lt;a href="https://softwareyoucan.love">software you can love&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My dream is one day to live a simple, modest, future earning a living building Mach for you and creating high-quality games for everyone. Please consider &lt;a href="https://github.com/sponsors/slimsag">sponsoring my work&lt;/a> if you believe in this vision.&lt;/p>
&lt;/div>
&lt;/div>
&lt;h2 id="thanks">Thanks&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Immense thank you to all those who helped make this release possible, to those who contribute regularly or in the past, and those who sponsor development. It means the world!&lt;/p>
&lt;div style="display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;">
&lt;img align="left" style="max-height: 12.5rem;" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/3173176/187348488-0b52e87d-3a48-421c-9402-be78e32b5a20.png">&lt;/img>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Join the &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/XNG3NZgCqp">Mach Discord server&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Check out &lt;a href="https://machengine.org">machengine.org&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Consider &lt;a href="https://github.com/sponsors/slimsag">sponsoring development&lt;/a> so we can do more of it!&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div></description></item><item><title>Announcing Mach nominated Zig versions</title><link>https://devlog.hexops.com/2024/announcing-nominated-zig/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://devlog.hexops.com/2024/announcing-nominated-zig/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today we&amp;rsquo;re announcing Mach nominated Zig versions, a sweet-spot between stable Zig and nightly Zig which offers a different balance of latest-and-greatest features and fixes, and less of a moving target.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you are in the Zig community, you likely fall into one of two categories:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>You target Zig nightly, a target which moves every day&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You target Zig stable, which may be released once or twice per year.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="the-challenge-of-using-zig-stable">The challenge of using Zig stable&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In recent years, Zig stable has about 2 releases per year. There are great benefits to using stable Zig:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>It is generally documented how to update/migrate your code to the new Zig version, rather than it being an ad-hoc process of discovery.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>The release is at a point where the Zig core team feels it is solid and ready to go (Zig releases are done when they are done, not usually timed.)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>These versions get nice numbers associated with them, package authors, distributions, etc. can easily target them.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>But, for a language that is developed quite quickly, and has yet to reach v1.0 stability.. when you find that an awesome new feature like the package manager, incremental compilation, or something else you care about has just landed in Zig nightly.. are you going to wait 6 months or more to get that change?&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-challenge-of-using-zig-nightly">The challenge of using Zig nightly&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Zig nightly is an ever-moving target. Although it is often nearly as stable as stable releases, that is not neccessarily the case during large refactors - such as the migration to the self-hosted compiler.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are benefits to using nightly, though! It means you are testing the latest version of Zig, and your project can exist in a sort of symbiotic relationship with the Zig project where you test new functionality, help provide feedback on it, discover new issues, and have a greater chance of getting them fixed/addressed while that code is on everyone&amp;rsquo;s mind.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Unlike stable Zig, you&amp;rsquo;re not integrating 6+ months of breaking changes into your codebase all at once (quite painful!) but rather doing so as the breaks happen. Since many others in the Zig community do target nightly Zig, there are often people around who can help you with upgrading your code.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One major downside, aside from death by a thousand paper cuts, is that everyone targets a different Zig nightly version. Often, it&amp;rsquo;s difficult to coordinate with others and keep your code compatible with theirs.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-challenge-mach-has-using-zig-nightly">The challenge Mach has using Zig nightly&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>We use Zig nightly, but we only periodically update the version.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Updating Mach&amp;rsquo;s Zig version involves updating a dependency tree of over &lt;a href="https://github.com/hexops/mach/issues/1135">40+ Zig repositories&lt;/a>, first updating the Zig code itself and testing manually, then updating their CI pipelines, then going and updating anyone who depends on that repository - from the bottom of the tree to the top!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We&amp;rsquo;ve built some serious automation to help with this process, but it is still painful - and it is also the case that every time we update our Zig version, our users need to do the same: we&amp;rsquo;re not just updating Zig for us, we&amp;rsquo;re updating Zig for every user of Mach.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This process has worked &lt;em>pretty&lt;/em> well for us, but the frequency of updates has always been ad-hoc, and when we do update it is a bit chaotic.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="we-need-our-ecosystem-of-40-packages-to-be-compatible">We need our ecosystem of 40+ packages to be compatible&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>If we haven&amp;rsquo;t updated our Zig version for a bit of time, then we end up with tens of outstanding pull requests by people who maybe don&amp;rsquo;t use &lt;em>all of Mach&lt;/em> but rather just parts of it, and they can become (rightfully!) fairly frustrated that getting their pull-request merged takes us a while.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We can&amp;rsquo;t just merge a one-off pull request to one repository, we have to update all 40+ to be compatible with the same Zig version.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://devlog.hexops.com/img/2024/so-many-pull-requests.png">&lt;img alt="so many pull requests" src="https://devlog.hexops.com/img/2024/so-many-pull-requests.png">&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="coordinating-outside-mach">Coordinating outside Mach&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Although Mach provides a lot of libraries, there are still many important aspects of gamedev we do not have yet. Some folks in the Mach community will pull in third-party Zig projects, like those from zig-gamedev, introducing another challenge in ensuring their code works with the same version.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="announcing-mach-nominated-zig-versions">Announcing Mach nominated Zig versions&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Today we&amp;rsquo;re formalizing the process we&amp;rsquo;ve (generally) been following. This formalization will make it easier for others to understand what we&amp;rsquo;re doing and when, and also make it easier for other projects to align their Zig version with Mach&amp;rsquo;s if they desire.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Throughout the year (aiming for the 4th day of the month), we will pick the latest Zig nightly version at that time and nominate it for use:&lt;/p>
&lt;table>
&lt;thead>
&lt;tr>
&lt;th>When&lt;/th>
&lt;th>What&lt;/th>
&lt;th>🚀 Other notable event&lt;/th>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/thead>
&lt;tbody>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>January&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>🚀 Mach version release&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>February&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>👋 Anticipated influx of new Machanists / Ziguanas&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>March&lt;/td>
&lt;td>⚡ Zig version nominated&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>April&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>May&lt;/td>
&lt;td>⚡ Zig version nominated&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>June&lt;/td>
&lt;td>⚡ Zig version nominated&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>July&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>🚀 Mach version release&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>August&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>👋 Anticipated influx of new Machanists / Ziguanas&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>September&lt;/td>
&lt;td>⚡ Zig version nominated&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>October&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>November&lt;/td>
&lt;td>⚡ Zig version nominated&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;tr>
&lt;td>December&lt;/td>
&lt;td>&lt;/td>
&lt;td>👋 Anticipated influx of new Machanists / Ziguanas&lt;/td>
&lt;/tr>
&lt;/tbody>
&lt;/table>
&lt;p>These versions will be noted as e.g. &amp;lsquo;2024.1.0-mach&amp;rsquo;, and will correspond to a specific Zig nightly version from that month.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The exact versions, which nightly version they map to, and the whole process (which is more involved), is &lt;a href="https://machengine.org/about/nominated-zig/">documented in full here&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>At the time of writing this, you&amp;rsquo;ll see that &lt;a href="https://machengine.org/about/nominated-zig/#202401">2024.1.0-mach&lt;/a> is marked as &amp;lsquo;in progress&amp;rsquo; - we will make sure that the Zig version we intend to nominate is at least compatible with all Mach projects before finalizing the nomination.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="a-sweet-spot-between-nightly-and-stable">A sweet spot between nightly and stable&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Mach&amp;rsquo;s nominated Zig versions provide a different set of tradeoffs, we believe it is a sweetspot between the two extremes of nightly and stable. You can benefit from the changes in Zig 2-3x faster than if you were using stable, and suffer less from the never-ending game of catch-up and incompatibilities between projects that nightly necessarily requires.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Other projects can target the same Zig version if they wish to be compatible with Mach Zig packages. For example, zig-gamedev is aiming to target the same versions. We encourage other gamedevs using Zig to do the same.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Projects that target nightly Zig can often be coincidentally compatible, too, since they possibly had a compatible Zig version around the time we nominated a Zig version for use.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="final-thoughts">Final thoughts&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>You can read more about the specifics of everything in the &lt;a href="https://machengine.org/about/nominated-zig">Mach documentation&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We&amp;rsquo;re currently working on nominating the first version, which will likely be finalized in the next week or so.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="thanks">Thanks&lt;/h2>
&lt;div style="display: flex; flex-direction: row; align-items: center;">
&lt;img align="left" style="max-height: 12.5rem;" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/3173176/187348488-0b52e87d-3a48-421c-9402-be78e32b5a20.png">&lt;/img>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Join the &lt;a href="https://discord.gg/XNG3NZgCqp">Mach Discord server&lt;/a> (check #discuss for this article)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Checkout &lt;a href="https://machengine.org">machengine.org&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Consider &lt;a href="https://github.com/sponsors/slimsag">sponsoring development&lt;/a> so we can do more of it!&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;/div></description></item></channel></rss>